<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

 Copyright 2004 The Apache Software Foundation.
 
 Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 limitations under the License.

-->
<document>
  <properties><title>Related projects</title></properties>
  <body>
   <section name="Related projects">
    <p>If you are interested in JaxMe 2, you may also want to take a look
      at the following related open source projects:</p>
	</section>
    <anchor id="jaxme1"/>
    <section name="JaxMe 1">
      <p><link href="ext:jaxme1">JaxMe 1</link> is the predecessor
      of JaxMe 2. It has a limited support of XML structures (mainly sequences
      and choices), but includes an integrated persistency framework that
      allows to read the objects from or write them into the database. The
      persistence framework includes support for JDBC mapping, XML:DB, the
      Tamino XML database, and EJB. The framework has the additional
      advantage of being quite mature and stable.</p>
    </section>


    <anchor id="jaxmexs"/>
    <section name="JaxMeXS">
      <p><link href="site:jaxmexs">JaxMeXS</link>, the JaxMe parser
      for XML schema, is internally used by JaxMe 2. It is written to be
      extensible, but not necessarily strict.</p>
      </section>

    <section name="JaxMeJS">
      <p><link href="site:jaxmejs">JaxMeJS</link>, the
      JaxMe Java source framework is a generic framework for writing
      Java source  generators. It used to be a part of JaxMe 1, but grew
      up to  be useful in itself and finally was moved to a separate
      distribution. JaxMe 2 is still based on the latest version, which
      also includes an SQL generator.</p>
      </section>

    <section name="eXist">
      <p><link href="site:exist">eXist</link> is a native XML database
      engine written in Java. It can be used standalone (via a dedicated
      TCP port), as part of a servlet engine (accessible via HTTP),
      or embedded into a Java application. This last approach is
      particularly useful for JUnit testing. JaxMe 1 uses eXist for
      testing its xml:db API.</p>
      </section>

    <section name="hsqldb">
      <p><link href="site:hsqldb">hsqldb</link> is an SQL database
      and also written in Java. Like eXist, it can be used in embedded
      mode and it is also used by JaxMe 1, JaxMe 2, and JaxMeJS for JUnit
      tests.</p>
      </section>
  </body>
</document>
